Guide to the Alpha Phi Alpha records, 1910-2016
Alpha Phi Alpha records, 1910-2016
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alpha Phi Alpha records, 1910-2016.
37-4-2509
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity.Alpha Chapter (Cornell University).
6.3 cubic ft. 5.1 terabytes
Correspondence, Publications, Memorabilia, Financial Records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files regarding Alpha Phi Alpha and its history, particularly the Cornell chapter.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Fraternity established at Cornell University, 1906; first black fraternity at Cornell, founded by Henry Arthur Callis, Charles Henry Chapman, Eugene Kinckle Jones, George Biddle Kelley, Nathaniel Allison Murray, Robert Harold Ogle, and Vertner Woodson Tandy.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence between Cornell Alumni News editor John Marcham and Mrs. Donald B. Saunders, September 30, 1968 and October 11, 1968; photographs of Robert H. Ogle, Vertner W. Tandy, George B. Kelley, and Henry A. Callis (chapter officers), and of meeting places and ceremonies; clippings and articles; and posters, handbills, brochures, and other miscellaneous items of Alpha Phi Alpha at Cornell University. Includes Round-Up Banquet programs. Early records from 1910-1929 include minutes of meetings, Annual Convention Reports, committee reports, scrapbook, and correspondence.
Contains materials related to the fraternity's Cornell pilgrimage (2005) and centennial celebration (2006), including a November 19, 2005 album signed by past presidents and members who attended the event and a poster signed by brothers who were present at the December 4, 2006 meeting of the New York Association of Chapters of Alpha.
Complete digitized set of the Sphinx Magazine available on a hard drive.
Master/raw video footage filmed by Rubicon Production, Inc. related to the production of the centennial documentary film entitled Alpha Phi Alpha: A Century of Leadership. Includes 95 Betacam SP Videocassette tapes; 4 DVM 60 Mini digital videocassette tapes; and 4 hard disk drives. The footage includes extensive interviews with many Alpha Phi Alpha fraternity brothers, as well as non-fraternity members; professionally staged re-enactments of historical moments and scenes from the Fraternity's history; and footage from events and activities at the General Conventions in Detroit and Philadelphia. Also an MP3 file containing an interview conducted with brother Dr. Donald Graham.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity.; Callis, Henry Arthur, 1887-1974.; Kelley, George B.; Ogle, Robert H.; Tandy, Vertner W., 1885-1949.; Alpha Phi Alpha--Centennial celebrations, etc..; Cornell University--Societies, etc.; Cornell University--Students.
Subjects:
Afro-American college students.; Greek letter societies.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 2 is restricted to members of any chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha with current fraternity ID card. For all other individuals Box 2 requires permission from current members of Alpha Chapter, Iota Iota Lambda Chapter, Alpha Chapter Alumni, or the National Historian, either in person or by signed letter. Discretion should be used when reproducing items from Box 2 regarding placing digital images online. Fraternity also provides list of members. All other boxes are not restricted.
RELATED MATERIAL
View the online exhibition on Alpha Phi Alpha here: http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/alpha
Additional digitized publications, including the Sphinx are online here: https://issuu.com/apa1906network
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Boxes 1
Series II. Programs, Documents, and news clippings
Boxes 1, 3, 7-10, Mapcases
Series III. Photographs and recordings
Boxes 1, 5-7
Series IV. Oaths, Initiation, and Convention related material
Box 2
Series V. Objects
Boxes 1
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence and business files
  - The Jewels Project, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Fraternity National Officers, other Chapters, and Vendors, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and News Clippings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Relating to 75th Anniversary and Alpha House, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Files pertaining to gaining historic landmark status for 421 North Albany Street, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Narrative Description of Property: Dennis-Newton House.
  - Correspondence from National office, other chapters, Alpha chapter alumni, 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence from National office, other chapters, Alpha chapter alumni, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series II. Programs, Documents, and news clippings
  - Dr. G. Alex Galvin News Clippings, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1988-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invitations, Programs, and Tickets, 1977-1985, (Bulk 1984) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brochures and Programs, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Round- Up and Party Flyers, Broadsides, 1983- ca. 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fifteenth Annual Round-Up Program, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Broadsides, 1980-2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Program Related Materials, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rayfer Mainor Materials, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Charles Harris Wesley Memorial Service Program, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Charles Harris Wesley Memorial Service Program (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Centennial celebration newspaper clipping., 2006 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Monthly Jewel Newsletters, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Undergraduate Round- Up XVIII, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Folders Undergraduate Round-Up Posters, 2003 (Folder 1)
  - News Clipping, February 2004 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ithakids Journal (Alpha Chapter Sponsored), Spring 2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Centennial program and exhibit
    - Centennial Pilgrimage Programs, November 2005 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cornell Reunion Event/ Centennial Program, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Centennial Convention: Ecumenical Service, Closing, 2006 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Composite Photo Facsimile, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity: A Centennial Celebration Introduction Labels and Exhibit Bibliography, 2006-12-04 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Exhibit Case Materials for Centennial, 2006-12-04 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Exhibit Case 3 Materials "Initiation Labels", Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Centennial Celebration: Case 5 Alpha Phi Alpha and the Great War Case Layout, Labels, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Case 1: Seven Jewels Then Brothers, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Centennial Celebration: Case 7 G. Alx Galvin Case Layouts, Labels, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Class Photo, College of Agriculture, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Cornell Pilgrimage Guestbook, 2005-11-19 (Box 9)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Centennial Exhibit: Case Four, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Misc for Exhibit, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha: Programs, Photos, etc, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha: Newspaper Clippings and Newsletters, 2009-2010 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha: Newspaper Clippings and Newsletters, 2016 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha: Photos and Pamphlets, 1917-1954 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Centennial celebration clippings, exhibition text, 2006 (Folder 1)
  - Signed Scroll (Original and one Copy) Commemorating the Meeting in Celebration of the Centennial of the Founding of Alpha Phi Alpha, 2006-12-04 (Folder 2)
- Series III. Photographs and recordings
  - Photograph of the Delegates Attending the Eastern Regional Convention, 1949 (Folder 2)
  - Photos from October 2016 events including the Robert F. Smith School dedication., 2016 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Portraits of the Seven Jewels (Box 3)
    These are photographs of the oil paintings that are in the lobby of Alpha Phi Alpha headquarters in Baltimore Maryland.
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 1A, 2003-07-31; V-10527 (Box 5, Folder Folder)
    Betacam tape
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 1B, 2003-07-31; V-10528 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 2A, 2003-07-31; V-10529 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 2B, 2003-07-31; V-10530 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 3A, 2003-07-31; V-10531 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 3B, 2003-07-31; V-10532 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 4A, 2003-07-31; V-10533 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 4B, 2003-07-31; V-10534 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 5A, 2003-07-31; V-10535 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 5B, 2003-07-31; V-10536 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 6A, 2003-07-31; V-10537 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 6B, 2003-07-31; V-10538 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 7A, Undated; V-10539 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 7B, Undated; V-10540 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 8A, 2003-08-01; V-10541 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 8B, 2003-08-01; V-10542 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 9A, 2003-08-01; V-10543 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 9B, 2003-08-01; V-10544 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 10A, 2003-08-01; V-10545 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 10B, 2003-08-01; V-10546 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 11A, 2003-08-01; V-10547 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 11B, 2003-08-01; V-10548 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 12B, 2003-08-01; V-10549 (Box 5)
    Note: No Row 12A
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 13A, 2003-08-02; V-10550 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 13B, 2003-08-02; V-10551 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 14A, 2003-08-02; V-10552 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 14B, 2003-08-02; V-10553 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 15B, 2003-08-02; V-10554 (Box 5)
    Note: No 15A
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 16B, 2003-08-02; V-10555 (Box 5)
    Note: No 16A
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 17B, 2003-08-02; V-10556 (Box 5)
    Note: No 17A
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 18A, 2003-08-03; V-10557 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 18B, 2003-08-03; V-10558 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 19A, 2003-08-03; V-10559 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 19B, 2003-08-03; V-10560 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 20A, 2003-08-03; V-10561 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 20B, 2003-08-03; V-10562 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 21A, 2003-08-03; V-10563 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 21B, 2003-08-03; V-10564 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 22A, 2003-08-03; V-10565 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 22B, 2003-08-03; V-10566 (Box 5)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 24B, 2003-08-03; V-10567 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 23A, 2003-08-03; V-10568 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 23B, 2003-08-03; V-10569 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 25B, 2003-08-04; V-10570 (Box 6)
    Note: No 25A
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 27B, 2003-08-03; V-10571 (Box 6)
    Note: No 26B
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 28A, 2003-08-04; V-10572 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 28B, 2003-08-04; V-10573 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 29A, 2003-08-04; V-10574 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 29B, 2003-08-04; V-10575 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 30A, 2003-08-04; V-10576 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 30B, 2003-08-04; V-10577 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception CR30, 2003-09-25; V-10578 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception CR31, 2003-09-25; V-10579 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception CR32, 2003-09-25; V-10580 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception CR33, 2003-09-25; V-10581 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception CR34, 2003-09-25; V-10582 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception CR35, 2003-09-25; V-10583 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception Interviews CR36, 2003-09-25; V-10584 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon-Alpha Congressional Black Caucus Reception Interviews CR37, 2003-09-25; V-10585 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha CR1- Dr. Huger, 2004-08-05; V-10586 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Philadelphia CR2, 2004-08-05; V-10587 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Philadelphia CR3, 2004-08-05; V-10588 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Philadelphia CR4, 2004-08-05; V-10589 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Philadelphia CR5: General Presidents Group Interview Pt 2 of 2, 2004-08-05; V-10590 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha phi Alpha Philadelphia CR6, 2004-08-06; V-10591 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions "Alpha" 27A, 2004-08-03; V-10592 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha phi Alpha Philadelphia CR7, 2004-08-06; V-10593 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha phi Alpha Philadelphia CR8, 2004-08-06; V-10594 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha CBC CR101, 2004-09-09; V-10595 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha CBC CR102, 2004-09-09; V-10596 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Howard University CR105, 2004-09-10; V-10597 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Howard University CR106, 2004-09-10; V-10598 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Howard University CR107, 2004-09-10; V-10599 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha Howard University CR108, 2004-09-10; V-10600 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha phi Alpha CR103, 2004-09-09; V-10601 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Productions Alpha Phi Alpha CR104, 2004-09-09; V-10602 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha CR40 Dr. Franklin Interview Pt 1, 2003-10-17; V-10603 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha CR41 Dr. Franklin Interview Pt 2, 2003-10-17; V-10604 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Akron CR1, 2005-02-03; V-10605 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Akron CR2, 2005-02-03; V-10606 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Akron CR3, 2005-02-03; V-10607 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Akron CR4, 2005-02-03; V-10608 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Akron CR5, 2005-02-04; V-10609 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Akron CR6, 2005-02-04; V-10610 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Lionel Richie Tape 1, 2005-02-21; V-10611 (Box 6)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Lionel Richie Tape 2, 2005-02-21; V-10612 (Box 6)
  - Alpha 50th Anniversary Convention, Undated; V-10613 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Colonel Charles McGee Interview, 2004-08-04; V-10614 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Interview Daryl Matthews Interview CR1, 2005-09-09; V-10615 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Daryl Matthews Interview CR2, 2005-09-09; V-10616 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Milton Davis Interview CR1, 2005-09-23; V-10617 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Milton Davis Interview CR2, 2005-09-23; V-10618 (Box 7)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Senator Brooke Pt 1, 2003-09-26; V-10619 (Box 7)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Senator Brooke Pt 2, 2003-09-26; V-10620 (Box 7)
  - Rubicon Alpha Phi Alpha Senator Brooke Pt 3, 2003-09-26; V-10621 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha dv#1, 2003-08-01; V-10622 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha dv#2, 2003-08-02; V-10623 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha dv#3, Undated; V-10624 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Akron CR1, 2005-02-03; V-10625 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Introduction, Cornell Pilgrimage, 2006; DVD-2616 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Board Meeting, MLK Memorial Rededication, Historical Exhibit, 2006; DVD-2617 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Opening Plenary Session, 2006; DVD-2618 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Centennial Fraternal Luncheon, Congressional Reception, 2006; DVD-2619 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Centennial symposium Pt 1, 2006; DVD-2620 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Centennial Symposium Luncheon, 2006; DVD-2621 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Centennial Symposium Pt 2, 2006; DVD-2622 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Public Program, 2006; DVD-2623 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Centennial Symposium Pt 3, 2006; DVD-2624 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: 21st Century Luncheon Final Symposium Session, Lionel Richie Performance, 2006; DVD-2625 (Box 7)
  - Centennial Convention: Howard University Photo, Final Plenary Session, Fashion Show, Black and Gold Banquet, 2006; DVD-2626 (Box 7)
  - Hard drive containing digital files.
    Includes Sphinx publication and other images. Also an MP3 file containing an interview conducted with brother Dr. Donald Graham recorded October 10, 2008 by brother Bertrand Odom-Reed. The interview was conducted by Burt Reed, another one of our fraternity brothers, in Dr. Graham's home in Ithaca. The subject of the interview was Dr. Graham's view of what the fraternity was in his mind, from when he joined to the present day. Also videos and photos from the Robert F. Smith School dedication, October 2016.
  - The Sphinx, Golden Jubilee, 1964; SR-55564 (Box LP)
    Digitized on CD-2046
  - The Sphinx, Golden Jubilee, 1964; CD-2046
    Copy of SR-5564
  - Material collected for the production of the centennial documentary film entitled Alpha Phi Alpha: A Century of Leadership
    - 4 hard drives worth of images and recordings
- Series IV. Oaths, Initiation, and Convention related material
  Restricted to members of any chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha with current fraternity ID card or written permission.
  - Order of Initiation (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oath of Secrecy - Oath of Allegiance, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Delegate's Report- 3rd Annual Convention, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chapter Report to the General Convention, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committee Reports, 1910-1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Delegate's Report-4th Annual Convention- Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Delegate's Report-5th Annual Convention- Columbus, Ohio, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Essays-Read during the year, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Delegate's Report-6th Annual Convention at Beta Chapter, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ritual Committee Reports, 1914-1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes- 8th Annual Convention, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Delegate's Report- 8th Annual Convention, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Prelim Questions- Vet, Chemistry, 1915-1918 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Essays, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Delegate's Report- 9th Annual Convention- Richmond, VA, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Committee on Student Affairs Report and Directories, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Committee Reports, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Delegate's Report- 10th Annual Convention- Rho, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Communications, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Order of Business- Recommendations, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Minutes- 15th Convention, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Minutes- 16th Convention, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Minutes 18th Convention- Detroit ,Michigan Delegate's Report, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence (Some World War I related Correspondence), 1917-1920s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1927 (Bulk 1927) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 22nd Convention Program, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Sphinx- Publication (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Certificates and Programs, 1915-1925 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Constitution and By- laws, 1910-1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1907-1920 (Bulk 1913-1916) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Ivy Leaf- Publication, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Copperplate Print Block (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series V. Objects
  - Centennial Pilgrimage Briefcase, November 2005 (Box 4)
  - Shingles (Box 1)